Guide to the Garvan-Sheldon Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Garvan-Sheldon collection
1796-1943
MS 232
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
(3 boxes)
Miscellaneous letters related to big game hunting, a photograph album of early contributors to Forest and Stream (with a letter from George Bird Grinnell identifying the photographs), diaries, miscellaneous writings and memorabilia all related to travel or hunting. The letters were removed from books in a library collected by Charles Sheldon and presented to Yale University by Francis P. Garvan in 1929.
Sheldon, Charles, 1867-1928
Garvan, Francis P. (Francis Patrick), 1875-1937
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of F. P. Garvan, 1929, and of Edward C. Tabler, 1946.
Scope and Contents
Miscellaneous letters related to big game hunting, a photograph album of early contributors to Forest and Stream (with a letter from George Bird Grinnell identifying the photographs), diaries, miscellaneous writings and memorabilia all related to travel or hunting. The letters were removed from books in a library collected by Charles Sheldon and presented to Yale University by Francis P. Garvan in 1929.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Forest and Stream; Big game hunting; Conservation of natural resources; Environmental protection; South Africa -- Description and travel; West (U.S.); Diaries; Baillie-Grohman, William A. (William Adolph), 1851-1921; Bannon, Henry Towne, 1867-1950; Bradley, Mary Hastings; Burlace, J. B.; Carter, James Morland; Colburn, Frederick S.; Deane, Ruthven, 1851-1934; Dresser, H. E. (Henry Eeles), 1838-1915; Ellsworth, Lincoln, 1880-1951; Fish, Frederick Studebaker; Fleischmann, Max C. (Max Charles), 1877-1951; Grinnell, George Bird, 1849-1938; Hallock, Charles, 1834-1917; Harrison, George Leslie, 1887-1958; Hazelton, William Chester, 1870-; Herbert, Henry William, 1807-1858; Jeffrey, W. J.; Lanman, Charles, 1819-1895; Leask, Thomas, 1839-1912; Lovell, Jonathan M.; Lyell, Denis D.; Mather, Amasa Stone, 1884-1920; McGuire, J. A.; McLellan, Isaac, 1806-1899; Menger, R. (Rudolph), 1851-1921; Chaworth Musters, Mrs., 1842-1912; Newall, David John Falconer; Phillipps-Wolley, Clive, 1854-1918; Phillips, W. S. (Walter Shelley), 1867-1940; Pringle, Walter, 1789-1834; Raymond, George B., 1841-; Robinson, Henry Mauris, 1868-1937; Sheffield, Frank; Shoemaker, William Lukens, 1822-; Stewart, William Drummond, Sir, 1795-1871; Tabler, Edward C.; Taylor, L.; Turnbo, S. C. (Silas Claiborn), 1844-1925; Uhagón y Guardamino, Francisco Rafael de, marqués de Laurencín, 1858-1927; Wagner, Henry R. (Henry Raup), 1862-1957; Webster, Edward Barton, 1868-1936; Werich, Jacob Lorenzo, 1860-; Whelen, Townsend, 1877-1961; Williams, A. Bryan; Wise, Lewis L. A.; Wroe, William E.; Young, Filson, 1876-1938
- Inventory, 1796-1943; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Baillie-Grohman, William A., b.1851, 1907 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    ALS to "Pike" [Warburton Mayer Pike, 1861-1915?] Removed from his Fifteen Years' Sport and Life. London. 1900.
  - Bannon, Henry Towne, 1867-, 1919 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    TLS to Charles M. Sheldon. Portsmouth, Ohio. Removed from Hunting Big Game in Northwestern America, by L. Taylor. 1919
  - Bannon, Henry Towne, 1867-, 1920 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    TLS to Charles Sheldon, Portsmouth, Ohio, concerning his brother, Arthur H. Bannon's A Hunter's Summer in Yukon Territory (Columbus, Ohio, 1911). Removed from A Hunter's Summer in Yukon Territory.
  - Bannon, Henry Towne, 1867-, 1920 December 9, December 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    ALS and TLS to Charles M. Sheldon. Portsmouth, Ohio. Removed from Bannon's Scioto Sketches. Chicago. 1920.
  - Bannon, Henry Towne, 1867-, 1920 October 29, November 4, 1921 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    3 TLS to William I. Starr. Portsmouth, Ohio. Removed from Bannon's Scioto Sketches. Chicago. 1920.
  - Bradley, Mary Hastings, [1923?] March 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    ALS to Mr. Sheldon [Chicago]. Removed from her On the Gorilla Trail. New York, London. 1922.
  - Burlace, J.B., 1919 November 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    TLS to Charles Sheldon. London. Removed from Rowland Ward's A Naturalist's Life Study. 1913.
  - Carter, Charles Moreland, 1920 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    TLS to Charles Sheldon with mimeographed statement about his hunting experiences. Removed from his Shooting in the Early Days. St. Joseph.
  - Colburn, Frederick S., 1928 June 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    2 ALS to Charles Sheldon. Chicago. Removed from his The Unbelievable Game Country. 1927
  - Deane, Ruthven, 1851-1934, 1910 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    ALS to Mr. Sheldon. Removed from Mary Dartt's On the Plains. Philadelphia. 1897
  - Deane, Ruthven, 1851-1934, 1920 October 23 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    ALS to Charles Sheldon, Chicago, enclosing an advertising folder issued by C.F. Periolat.
  - Deane, Ruthven, 1851-1934, 1921 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    ALS to Charles Sheldon, Chicago, accompanying a photograph of Sir James Le Moine. Removed from Le Moine's The Explorations of Jonathan Oldbuck. Quebec. 1889.
  - Dresser, Henry Eeles, 1838-1915, 1898 February 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    AN to "Tegelmeur" [W.B. Tegetmeier], with a copy of the portrait of "an old Irishman" [Horace William Wheelwright] referred to in the letter. London. Removed from A Spring and Summer in Lapland. 1864.
  - Ellsworth, Lincoln, 1880-, 1916 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    ALS to Charles Sheldon, New York. Removed from The Last Wild Buffalo Hunt by Lincoln Ellsworth. New York. 1916.
  - Fish, F. Studebaker, 1920 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    TLS to Charles Sheldon, Philadelphia, concerning his A Hunting Trip in Jackson's Hole, Wyoming by F.S. Fish, 1913
  - Fleischmann, Maximiliam Charles, 1912 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    2 TLS to Charles Sheldon. Cincinnati. Removed from After Big Game in Arctic and Tropic by Max. C. Fleischmann. Cincinnati. 1909.
  - Harrison, George L., 1914 April 14, 1916 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    2 TLS to Charles Sheldon. Philadelphia. Removed from The Recollections of William Finaughty. Philadelphia. 1916.
  - Hazelton, William C., 1921 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    ALS to Charles Sheldon. Elgin, IL. Removed from In Wildfowling Tales. Compiled and published by William C. Hazelton. Chicago. 1921.
  - Herbert, Henry William, 1807-1858, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    ALS to Rev. R.W. Griswold.
  - Jeffrey, W.J., 1920 November 26 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    TL to Charles Sheldon.
  - Lanman, Charles, 1819-1895, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    "Story of a Virginia Hunter," Ms story.
  - Leask, Thomas, 1861-1880 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    "Hunting and Trading Experiences in South Africa, 1862 [i.e. 1861] - 1880." Typescript carbons of diaries. 2 v.
  - Lovell, Jno. M., 1796 April (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Lovell's artillery minute book, West Point.
  - Lyell, Denis D., 1928 December 17 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    ALS to Charles Sheldon. Moffat, Dumfrieshire, Scotland. Removed from his The African Elephant and Its Hunters. London. 1924. Photograph enclosed.
  - McGuire, James A., 1919 December 17, 1920 November 26 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    2 TLS to Charles Sheldon. Denver, Colo. Removed from McGuire's In the Alaska-Yukon Gamelands. Cincinnati. [1921].
  - McLellan, Isaac, 1806-1899, [1886] January 16 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    ALS to Henry Moore. Greenport, [Long Island].
  - Mather, Amasa Stone, 1884-1920, 1911 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    ALS to Charles Sheldon. Removed from Mather's Extracts from Letters, Diaries… Cleveland. 1910.
  - Menger, Rudolph, 1900 September 24 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    ALS to editor of Scientific American [1913]. With letter from the Scientific American. Removed from his Texas Nature Observations. San Antonio. 1913.
  - Musters, Lina Chaworth [Mrs. John Chaworth Musters], 1894 March 4 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    ALS to Mr. Sheldon. Biryham. Nittingham. Removed from Book of Hunting Songs and Sport collected by Musters.
  - Newall, David J.F., 1891 June 1 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    ALS to "My dear Stewart" [Newton Stewart]. Ryde, I.W. Removed from Newall's The Highlands of India. London. 1882.
  - Phillipps-Wolley, Clive, 1854-, 1906 February 17, April 9. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    2 ALS to Charles Sheldon. Pier Island, B.C. Removed from his Big Game Shooting. London. 1894.
  - Phillips, Walter Shelley, 1867-, n.y. April 17 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    ALS to C.S. Sheldon signed "El Comancho". Removed from Clewley's Sportsman's Handbook. Seattle, ca. 1911. Edited by "El Comancho."
  - Pringle, Thomas, 1789-1834, 1833 December 6 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    ALS to Samuel Carter Hall. Highyule. Removed from African Sketches by Thomas Pringle. London. 1834.
  - Raymond, George B., 1841-, 1906 April 29 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    ALS from George B. Raymond to Charles Sheldon. Removed from Raymond's Catalogue of Books on Sport. New York. 1904.
  - Raymond, George B., 1841-, 1909 December 12 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    ALS to Ruthven Deane. Removed from Raymond's Catalogue of Books on Sport. New York. 1904.
  - Robinson, Henry. M., 1908 October 23 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    ALS to George Bird Grinnell. New York. Removed from Col. Cook's Observations on Fox Hunting. London. 1923.
  - Sheffield, Frank, 1902 October 8 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    ALS to the editor of Truth. [London]. Removed from Sheffield's How I Killed the Tiger. London. 1902.
  - Sheldon, Charles, 1867-1928, 1922 May 28 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    ALS to Henry Worcester Smith. [Washington, D.C.] Removed from J.J. Pringle's Twenty Years Snipe Shooting. New York. 1899.
  - Shoemaker, William Lukens, 1822-, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Poem "To Charles Lanman." Washington, D.C. First published in the Literary World. Boston, No. 2, Jan. 15, 1881. Removed from Recollections of Curious Characters by Charles Lanman. Edinburgh. 1881.
  - Stewart, Sir William Drummond, 1835-1845 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Typewritten copies of letters to William L. Sublette.
  - Tabler, Edward C., 1943 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Carbon copy of typewritten essay on Captain Cornwallis Harris.
  - Taylor, L., 1919 December 22 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    TLS to Charles Sheldon. McDermitt, Ohio. Removed from Hunting Big Game in Northwestern North America by L. Taylor. 1910.
  - Turnbo, Silas C., 1919 February 10, February 27, April 8 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    1 ALS and 2 APS to Charles Sheldon. Pontiac, Missouri. Removed from Fireside Stories of the Early Days in the Ozarks.
  - Uhagon y Guardamino, Francisco Rafael de, 1858-1927, 1903 December 14 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    ALS to Charles Sheldon. Removed from Uhagon's La Caza. Madrid. 1888.
  - Wagner, Henry Raup, b.1862 Y.1884, 1921 April 8 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    TLS to Charles Sheldon. Berkeley, Calif. Removed from his The Plains and the Rockie s. San Francisco. 1921.
  - Wagner, Henry Raup, b.1862 Y.1884, n.y. July 2 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    ALS to Charles Sheldon. Removed from Wagner's The Plains and the Rockies. San Francisco. 1921.
  - Webster, Edward B., 1922 February 7 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    TNS to Charles Sheldon. Port Angeles, Wash. Removed from his The Kings of the Olympics. Port Angeles. 1920.
  - Werich, J. Lorenzo, 1860-, 1923 February 21, March 7 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    2 ALS to Charles Sheldon. Logansport, Ind. Removed from 2 prospectuses of Pioneer Hunters of the Kankakee by Werich. 1920.
  - Whelen, Townsend, b.1887, 1920 November 26 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Ballistic data on .256 Mannlicher rifle by Major Townsend Whelen. TL from W.J. Jeffrey & Co. to Charles Sheldon.
  - Williams, A. Bryan, 1925 October 21 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    TLS to Charles Sheldon. Removed from Williams' Game Trails in British Columbia. London. 1925.
  - Wise, Lewis L.A., 1880 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Diary of a trip around the world and short diaries of other trips.
  - Wroe, William E., 1917 April 1, 1920 January 21 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    1 TLS and 1 ALS to Charles Sheldon. Chicago. With 2 photographs. Removed from James Blomfield's Rod, Gun and Palette in the High Rockies. Chicago. 1914.
  - Young, Filson, 1931 July 7 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    TLS to Langhorn Gibson. [London]. With carbon of TL from Langhorn Gibson to Filson Young. Removed from Young's With the Battle Cruisers. London. 1921.
  - Prairie and Mountain Life: typescript of sketches published 1843 Apr-1844 Mar, [pre-1931] (Box 2, Folder 48-49)
  - Record of game shot at Sandringham, England, 1843 January 14-17 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Hallock, Charles, 1834-1917, collector, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
    Photograph album of pictures of early contributors to Forest and Stream. 50 photographs.
  - Cantwell, George G. and Alex Starbuck, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
    Photographs removed from the photograph album of contributors to Forest and Stream. (Folder 51)
  - Grinnell, George Bird, 1849-1938, 1923 February 27 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    TLS to Charles Sheldon identifying the photographs in the album (Folder 51), some with personal reminiscences. 7p.